<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Bleep Systems</title>
  <link href="http://blog.bleepsystems.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.bleepsystems.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-10-01T14:43:43+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.bleepsystems.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Bleep Systems</name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title>What is the Best Way to Structure the Checkout Process?</title>
    <link href="http://blog.bleepsystems.com/2011/what-is-the-best-way-to-structure-the-checkout-process/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-25T14:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.bleepsystems.com/2011/what-is-the-best-way-to-structure-the-checkout-process</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A question that keeps cropping up recently is from customers who want to know the best way to structure the checkout process. Firstly you should never stray from the globally accepted online shopping metaphor which is how all good web stores operate and how most people would expect to buy a product. Some stores insist on putting obstacles in the way like signing in, but all this will do is, well, get in peoples way. Stick with this method and you will be fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The normal process to buy something is this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discover products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add products to cart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checkout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review cart and change totals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter details and payment information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Receive confirmation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This article is talking about step 5 or more specifically the journey from 4 to 5 then 6. The customer has a full cart and now they want to pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two ways of structuring this part of the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Bank Hosted&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the customer leaves your site and is taken to a 3rd party (normally the bank, but perhaps Paypal) site where they pay and then are taken back to your website for confirmation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here at &lt;a href=&quot;http://bleepsystems.com&quot;&gt;Bleep&lt;/a&gt; we find that there is a common misconception that this is less desirable from a user experience perspective. We think it depends. Many people are much more comfortable putting their credit card details into the website of a bank rather than that of a site which perhaps they have never seen before. This might be especially true if your site does not have a physical address and phone number on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another advantage of this method is that the bank deals with all the security requirements regarding credit card numbers and data privacy laws. The merchant never has to deal with any of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This route often allows for the hosted bank to implement any additional security checks such as the ‘Verified by Visa’ check. Sometimes implementing the hosted solution is the only way to get such checks as is the case with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.anz.com/small-business/products-services/merchant-services/internet-payment-solutions/egate/&quot; title=&quot;eGate&quot;&gt;eGate&lt;/a&gt; from ANZ in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method although a little more disjointed is perfectly valid and is used successfully in thousands of places on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Merchant Hosted&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most new customers we get often think this is the way to go and the reasons why are obvious. The main one being that all the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk&quot;&gt;big&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://play.com&quot;&gt;etailers&lt;/a&gt; structure the checkout process this way. In the eyes of new etailers - if you do it this way you must be a large, successful and powerful. To a certain degree this is true and it is because of this fact that people are willing to give you there credit card details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this structure the customer never leaves your site. All the payment forms including billing, shipping and card details done within the brand of the main site. The payment details are submitted securely to the bank and a message sent back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This structure takes the longest to implement and test from a development point of view. It has the major disadvantage that each time the bank changes their system, or adds additional security it is necessary to spend money implementing the changes. Someone else&amp;#8217;s decision to change something can end up costing you money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any experience with any of the above or you think we could improve the answer to this question then please leave a comment below.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Site Search Analytics in E-commerce (SSA)</title>
    <link href="http://blog.bleepsystems.com/2011/site-search-analytics-ssa/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-20T20:27:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.bleepsystems.com/2011/site-search-analytics-ssa</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Site search analytics (SSA) is an emerging form of site analytics that studies search query data to discover patterns in site use. Here at Bleep we’ve been working hard to understand how to benefit from the information this type of analysis provides which drive users to buying products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any searchable ecommerce site is sitting on top of hugely valuable and usually under-exploited data: logs that capture what users are searching for, how often each query was searched, and how many results each query retrieved. Search queries are gold: they are real data that show us exactly what users are searching for in their own words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data you obtain from internal search analytics is essentially a resource that tells you what your visitors cannot find on your site. For example, if you sell clothing and you have hundreds of searches for &amp;#8220;white t-shirts&amp;#8221; but you don’t sell them, it might just be worth looking into selling white t-shirts. If you receive a lot of searches for white t-shirts, but you have a link to your white t-shirts category right on your navigation bar, then there’s a possibility that there is something wrong with your site navigation’s design and effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your top search term is ‘opening hours’ you need to make sure that the right page is at the top of your search results. Studying what users put in and analysing what these search terms bring back will help you a lot. If you can improve the UX and sales by even a small percentage then it has been worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concrete Ways to use SSA in Ecommerce&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To develop useful search system. To do this you need get close up to your search system. SSA will help you understand how people entered searches, where they were when they entered them, and how they interpreted the search results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Navigation. If certain pages generate more activity than others you need to find out why. Perhaps certain navigational options are missing or are just confusing. SSA asks questions in these areas (which you often may take for granted). What works navigationally for you might not be obvious for others.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To improve your content. Are there any queries that bring back no results? Is this because you lack the content or that the search is in effective in bringing back the accurate results. is the relevant content mistitled? Or poorly written? SSA will help you determine what content is missing and what to do to existing content to make sure it gets found.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To discover patterns. Can you structure the search data in different ways and examine it? Are there any patterns? Can you use those patterns to determine what types of metadata and content are the most important to your searchers? Can you detect changes in seachers’ behavior and needs that are seasonal? Patterns describe behavior.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To highlight failure. When searches return no results or poor results - ask why? And what can we do to fix those problems and improve performance?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To examine user behavior. What happens during a specific search session? How do searchers’ needs and understanding of the content change as they search?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To analyse the audience. How might we uncover the differences between audience segments and their information needs? And how might we better address those differing needs?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using Google Analytics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Google Analytics V5 it is easy to get started with SSA. If your website has a search box, go ahead and perform a search to see the URL of the search results. For example your search results might be http://yoursite.com/?s=searchtermhere. Once you have this for your site, click on the settings wheel icon in the top right corner of your Analytics menu bar and find your Profile Settings. Under Site Search Settings, select the option to ‘Do track Site Search’ and enter s as the query parameter (or the one that fits your site’s URL structure).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Rise of Subscription Commerce</title>
    <link href="http://blog.bleepsystems.com/2011/the-rise-of-subscription-commerce/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-15T05:56:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.bleepsystems.com/2011/the-rise-of-subscription-commerce</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Subscription based ecommerce businesses (“subcom” for short) are on the rise. In a typical situation, a subcom business will send their customers (“the subscribers”) a box full of products on a regular basis. Very often these businesses try to attract customers with specific needs. For example, a subcom appealing to new mothers may send their subscribers a box of baby care items each month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.kissmetrics.com/subcom/&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&#8217;[blank] &#8217; src=&#8217;http://blog.kissmetrics.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/subcom-sm.jpg&#8217; width=&#8221; height=&#8221; alt=&#8217;[100% 100%] [The Rise of Subscription Commerce]&#8217; title=&#8217;[100% 100%] [The Rise of Subscription Commerce]&#8217;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
