<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Bleep Systems</title>
  <link href="http://blog.bleepsystems.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.bleepsystems.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-09-20T21:36:14+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.bleepsystems.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Neil Charlton</name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title>Site Search Analytics (SSA)</title>
    <link href="http://blog.bleepsystems.com/blog/2011/site-search-analytics-ssa/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-20T20:27:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.bleepsystems.com/blog/2011/site-search-analytics-ssa</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Site search analytics (SSA) is an emerging form of site analytics that studies search query data to discover patterns in site use. Here at Bleep we’ve been working hard to understand how to benefit from the information this type of analysis provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any organization that has a searchable web site or intranet is sitting on top of hugely valuable and usually under-exploited data: logs that capture what users are searching for, how often each query was searched, and how many results each query retrieved. Search queries are gold: they are real data that show us exactly what users are searching for in their own words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data you obtain from internal search analytics is essentially a resource that tells you what your visitors cannot find on your site. For example, if you sell clothing and you have hundreds of searches for &amp;#8220;white t-shirts&amp;#8221; but you don’t sell them, it might just be worth looking into selling white t-shirts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you receive a lot of searches for white t-shirts, but you have a link to your white t-shirts category right on your navigation bar, then there’s a possibility that there is something wrong with your site navigation’s design and effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your top search term is ‘opening hours’ you need to make sure that the right page is at the top of your search results. Studying what users put in and analysing what these search terms bring back will help you a lot. If you can improve the UX by even a small percentage then it has been worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Google Analytics V5 it is easy to get started with SSA. If your website has a search box, go ahead and perform a search to see the URL of the search results. For example your search results might be http://yoursite.com/?s=searchtermhere. Once you have this for your site, click on the settings wheel icon in the top right corner of your Analytics menu bar and find your Profile Settings. Under Site Search Settings, select the option to ‘Do track Site Search’ and enter s as the query parameter (or the one that fits your site’s URL structure).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Rise of Subscription Commerce</title>
    <link href="http://blog.bleepsystems.com/blog/2011/the-rise-of-subscription-commerce/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-15T05:56:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.bleepsystems.com/blog/2011/the-rise-of-subscription-commerce</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Subscription based ecommerce businesses (“subcom” for short) are on the rise. In a typical situation, a subcom business will send their customers (“the subscribers”) a box full of products on a regular basis. Very often these businesses try to attract customers with specific needs. For example, a subcom appealing to new mothers may send their subscribers a box of baby care items each month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.kissmetrics.com/subcom/&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&#8217;[blank] &#8217; src=&#8217;http://blog.kissmetrics.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/subcom-sm.jpg&#8217; width=&#8221; height=&#8221; alt=&#8217;[100% 100%] [The Rise of Subscription Commerce]&#8217; title=&#8217;[100% 100%] [The Rise of Subscription Commerce]&#8217;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
